GORDON: Previously on Gotham...
- Hello.
- What's wrong with you?
I let him out of his cage, and
he helped me get out of mine.
You're him. The Riddler.
Hi, Lee.
Butch?
- You're alive.
- Huh?
TABITHA: Oh, Butch. I tried.
Tabby, I'm gonna find a
way to get back to the old me.
I promise.
GORDON: Tell me about
your mother, Jerome?
- Did she have any enemies?
- No.
And do you have
any other family?
The circus is my family.
JEROME: Now, to free the rest of
our cronies and blow this pop stand.
BRUCE: I could have killed Jerome
after he kidnapped me, and I didn't.
Any harm he does
now, I share a part of it.
I saw Jerome tonight.
He was looking for the
name of a school, St. Ignatius.
Stay the hell away
from that madman.
I'll see you at
St. Ignatius, Jim.
Sir.
Sir?
MAN: Can I help you?
My name is Bruce Wayne.
I'm looking for Jerome Valeska.
Has he been here?
MAN: I didn't have the
pleasure of meeting Mr. Valeska.
However, I did
speak with his friend,
the one with the top hat.
- Jervis Tetch.
- Yes.
That's the fellow.
He was very polite.
What did he want?
MAN: The name of a student
who graduated St.
Ignatius 10 years ago.
Xander Wilde.
Fine young boy. Very bright.
Did Tetch tell you why
Jerome was looking for him?
No.
But he did have a message
for you.
(BEEPING)
(BRAKES SCREECHING)
Listen to me. You're being
hypnotized by Jervis Tetch.
You don't wanna
press that button.
But I have to.
- He's depending on me.
- GORDON: Bruce!
Step away from him.
BRUCE: Please.
- Hand me the detonator.
- MAN: I want to.
But I can't.
BRUCE: Captain Gordon, look.
He's under Jervis' spell.
Oh!
(POCKET WATCH TICKING)
(GRUNTS)
Get down!
(CLINKING)
JEROME: Hear ye, hear ye!
I'd like to officially welcome
you all to our first ever
Mandatory Brunch Meeting.
Now, I know what
you're all thinking.
Why have I gathered
this legion of horribles?
That has a nice ring to it.
Write that down, will ya?
Well, back when I was in Arkham,
I came up with a plan to
turn this city into a madhouse.
Now I am on the cusp
of making that happen,
but I need help from all of...
Put all questions
on ice until the end.
Danke schön.
Mr. Oswald.
Thank you for doing your
part in hosting us today.
Anything for an old friend.
Crane.
Where are we at with the...
You know what.
It's coming along dreadfully.
Oh, Pun-worthy. Excellent.
Freeze, Ice Man,
you're our science guy.
We're gonna need a lab.
A big one.
Easy enough.
Mmm. Now, all we need
is Mr. Tetch to return
with some very
important information.
Use the tongs, Carl.
You still haven't told us
how you're going to
take over the underworld.
Who says I wanna do that?
I'm an artist.
I just wanna paint
the town crazy.
Once that happens, I could care
less how you horribles rip the city apart.
I'm in. Let's do this.
Well, not yet.
Nothing can happen until we have
our one last essential ingredient.
(DOOR CLOSES)
The one thing that'll
tie it all together.
Who is Xander Wilde?
I don't know.
Did Jerome say anything
at his uncle's diner?
Anything that could tell us
why he's going after him?
If I knew that, Captain,
I would tell you.
Would you?
How can I trust
anything you say?
I told you not to come
here and you did anyway.
Damn it, you could
have been killed.
All right, Captain, I think
you've made your point.
And you?
Did you know he was
going after Jerome?
Indeed, I did, yes.
If he gets involved
in this case again,
I'll press charges. We clear?
Come on, son.
HARVEY: Yo!
I just talked to
an administrator.
Xander Wilde was some
kind of child prodigy.
Now he's a hotshot structural
engineer at Meyer and Hayes.
What does Jerome
want with an engineer?
Maybe he wants him
to build him something.
Let's go.
(MUZAK PLAYING)
(WHISTLING)
(BLOWING)
I used to be a great whistler.
Mmm-hmm.
Um, yeah, hi.
I'm here to see
Xander Wilde. And, no...
I don't have an appointment.
(WHIMPERS)
Don't bother going to
security. They're all...
- (RECEPTIONIST SCREAMING)
- Headless.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
All right. If you would all
please look at the rendering,
you'll notice that there are several
interesting engineering problems
- that present themselves. Mostly...
- (GUN COCKING)
(PEOPLE GASPING)
Oh, don't get up.
I won't waste too
much of your time.
(OBJECT SHATTERING)
I've got a business proposition.
Tell me what I want to know
and you don't get turned inside out.
Please, don't...
Don't hurt anyone.
Where is Xander Wilde?
- He's... He's not here.
- Yeah.
I'm not blind. Maybe you are.
Um, you know? Hmm?
No one does. He's
never set foot in this office.
- Okay.
- (GROANS)
- (ALL GASP)
- Oh, God!
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
(STAMMERING) We've never met.
I've only ever
communicated with him
through a proxy.
- Proxy?
- Yeah.
(LAUGHING)
That slippery little sucker
thinks he can get away from me.
(GROANS)
Where can I find
this proxy, pray tell?
(STAMMERING)
I'll tell you. I'll tell you.
- (ELEVATOR BELL DINGS)
- (PANICKED CLAMORING)
Don't take the elevator!
(PEOPLE SCREAMING)
Jimbo!
Old buddy, old pal,
it's great to see ya!
Drop the gun.
You are such a stick in the mud.
Give it up, clown boy!
Hey.
Knock, knock.
You were supposed
to say, "Who's there?"
- Thank you, Francis.
- Take down their statements.
Hey, Jim. Same story all around.
No one knows Xander.
No one even met him.
Apparently, he had a proxy
who handled his
dealings with the company.
Hayes was the only one
who knew their identity,
but obviously, he's not talking.
So, we have to figure out
another way to find Xander.
I'm ahead of you.
We looked into it.
No driver's license. No known
addresses. Guy's a ghost.
Everything that's happened
in the last 24 hours,
the breakout, Tetch,
it's all been about
Jerome finding this guy.
I don't think it has anything to
do with him being an engineer.
- This seems personal.
- Makes sense.
I mean, Jerome went to
his uncle to look for him.
Yeah, so how are they connected?
What's up?
Is that Wayne Plaza?
Take a look at the
initials of the engineer.
- "X.W." Xander Wilde.
- Uh-huh.
Looks like we're gonna
have to go talk to the kid.
He's gonna be
thrilled to see you.
What time is it?
ALL: Riddle time!
(ROCK MUSIC PLAYING)
What time is it?
ALL: Riddle time!
That's right! It's riddle time
- at the Riddle Factory!
- ALL: The Riddle Factory!
(ALL CHEERING)
Our first contestant is...
Lars.
(IN GERMAN ACCENT) From
the now-defunct biker gang,
The Street Demonz.
(IN NORMAL VOICE) It's been
a rough go of it lately, huh, Lars?
I've fallen on hard times.
But I'm damn happy to
be here with you, Riddler.
That's the narrow spirit I love.
Now, you know the rules.
I ask a riddle, you answer
correctly, you ask me one.
You win 'em both,
and you're walking out of
here with cold hard cash!
(CROWD CHEERING)
Lila.
Prepare the timer.
I am heavy forward, but
backward I am not. What am I?
(CREAKS)
Okay. I'm heavy forward...
But backward I'm not.
Okay, wait... Wait a minute.
No, no, I know this.
It's...
No, no, I know this. Um...
Wait, wait, wait.
It's the hour glass.
(BUZZER SOUNDING)
The answer is, "Ton." T-O-N.
Backwards I am, "Not."
Sorry, Lars.
ALL: Spin the wheel!
Spin the wheel!
You hear them, Lars.
It's time to spin the
wheel of misfortune!
ALL: Spin the wheel!
Spin the wheel!
Lila, please.
ALL: Spin the wheel!
Spin the wheel!
(BELL DINGING)
My personal favorite.
Rabid sack of rats.
(PEOPLE LAUGHING)
Yeah!
- (RATS SQUEAKING)
- LEE: All right, that's enough. Enough!
NYGMA: Doc Thompkins.
What brings Your Majesty
down to our rabble?
How are you doing, Ed?
Haven't seen you since
we put Oswald on ice.
Well, I'm doing far
better than Sofia Falcone,
from what I understand.
Whatever the hell
this is, it's over.
I don't think so.
Ladies and gentlemen,
our queen has just informed me
she wants to shut us down.
How do you feel about that?
(CROWD BOOING)
You hear that?
That's the sound of democracy.
The people have spoken.
And my name is The Riddler.
Okay.
You wanna be entertained?
Hold this, will you?
- Then I'll beat him.
- CROWD: Oh!
You can't be serious.
You realize what
happens when you lose.
I know. I spin the wheel.
But if I win, you
shut this place down.
(CROWD JEERING)
We have our next contestant!
(CROWD CHEERING)
JEROME: Got any
ice cream in there?
I've always had a soft
spot for Chunky Monkey.
I was wondering
when you would come.
Me? That's very flattering.
So, tell me, Little Miss
Proxy, where is he?
I'll never tell you.
Hmm,
I don't know.
See...
I can be very persuasive.
See that?
Yeah. I was
wondering about that.
You got, like, a big
dog or something?
No.
That's how I'm going
to transport you.
Hmm?
(JEROME GROANS)
I've got him.
Butch?
I had heard you were different.
But I will be honest...
I like it.
What do you want?
I assume you've heard
about the Arkham breakout.
Well, I just came from
brunch with Jerome Valeska,
and let's just say that
he has plans for Gotham.
What kind of plans?
That part wasn't entirely clear.
Seemed to involve
a great deal of paint.
No matter.
I have seen his kind come and
go. Jerome Valeska will flame out.
And in the rubble,
I will reclaim the underworld.
I could use a good
man like you by my side.
(CHUCKLES)
You must be all out of
allies to come looking for me.
Don't be modest.
With your brute
strength and my brains,
we will be unstoppable.
I did that job.
- I'm my own man now.
- (PENGUIN LAUGHS)
Really?
Because from where I am, you
look like a man who has nothing.
You'd be wise to watch
what you say to me.
- I'm not the same man you remember.
- And neither am I.
Look at the two of us.
We used to run
this town. Together.
We were friends.
Look, you want your
old life back, so do I.
- We are the same.
- Wrong!
You can have your old life back.
I can't. Look at me.
Tabitha will never
love me again.
Slaughter Swamp
turned me into a monster!
Now get out of here.
If I ever see you again,
I'll pop your head
off like a flower.
(COUGHS)
(DOOR OPENS)
Let me get this straight.
You tell us to stay out
of your investigation
and now you want our help?
- Subtle.
- We have reason to believe
your father met
with Xander Wilde.
Well, if he did, he certainly
would have made a note of it.
What was the name
of that building again?
Wayne Plaza.
He was a meticulous
note taker, Thomas.
He organized
everything by project.
Let's see. Wayne Gardens...
Wayne Hospital...
Aha, here we go, Wayne Plaza.
All right.
Why, you're bang on
the money there, Captain.
Xander Wilde. Says he went
to meet him to finalize the plans.
No address, just the name
of the street, Ainslie Drive.
It's out past Buxton
by the old rock quarry.
BRUCE: This man
must've been very important
if my father went out of
his way to meet him alone.
I'm starting to think he isn't just
some recluse hiding from the world.
He's hiding from Jerome.
(LAUGHING)
How interesting.
(GRUNTS)
Oh! Oh,
you are incorrigible.
And then again,
you always were.
(LAUGHS)
Wait. Or was that me?
Sometimes I get
so confused, I...
I can't remember.
(LAUGHS MANIACALLY)
You didn't have to
run away like that.
You see,
I would never hurt you,
Xander.
I love you.
(LAUGHS MANIACALLY)
I can't wait to see you.
Did you think about me?
I know that you did.
- I'm gonna squeeze you until you pop.
- (BEEPING)
Where the hell is the house?
(DOORBELL BUZZING)
James Gordon.
Here to see Xander Wilde.
So this whole
joint's underground?
Mr. Wilde values his privacy.
How long has he lived here?
He finished construction
six years ago.
- Echo, 496.
- Welcome, Miss Echo.
He'll see you now.
Thank you for
seeing us, Mr. Wilde.
I expected you
might come, Captain.
HARVEY: My God.
There's two of them.
May I put my hands
down now, gentlemen?
Please?
Apologies, Mr. Wilde,
you took us by surprise.
It's understandable.
You can call me Jeremiah.
That's name my mother gave me.
You solved her murder,
and Captain Gordon, I owe
you a debt of gratitude for that,
and for putting Jerome in
Arkham, where he belongs.
He never mentioned you before.
No, I suppose you wouldn't know
from the letters my mother sent me,
he never spoke
of me after I left.
Left where?
The Circus.
They hid me away to
protect me from him.
See, we are always
different, Jerome and I.
From an early age, I showed a
proficiency for maths and design
and Jerome, mainly the
mutilation of alley cats.
On my 10th birthday, he
held a cake knife to my throat.
A few weeks later,
he lit my bed on fire.
It was like living
in a nightmare.
My mother knew, eventually,
one day he would succeed, so...
One night, my uncle came
to my room while Jerome slept
and told me that he
was taking me away.
I had no idea where,
but I kissed my mother goodbye,
told her I love her, and
I never saw her again.
He took you to St. Ignatius.
Got a new name, new life, where I
was finally able to live without fear.
But in my heart,
I knew one day Jerome
would come for me.
Well, that day is today, pops.
GORDON: We have reason to
believe Jerome knows where you are.
We need to move
you to a safe location
until we can apprehend him.
That won't be
necessary, gentlemen.
I've spent the bulk of my life
preparing for this eventuality.
I am safest here in my home.
Not anymore. Jerome
knows the name of your proxy.
He got it from your boss
just before he executed him.
I heard about Jerome
visiting Alan Hayes.
It's tragic.
But the proxy's name I
gave to Alan was a fake.
You're lying.
I beg your pardon?
There's something
about this guy that's fishy.
Security cameras
outside were turned on,
so why are the
monitors in here off?
I don't see why that
is any of your concern.
Now, if you'll excuse
me, I'm a very busy man.
Yeah, I'm sure that you are.
Please don't touch that.
That's very sensitive equipment.
(SCOFFS)
(GRUNTING)
Oh, yeah. I'd say that's
pretty damn sensitive.
Ladies and gentlemen, a gauntlet
has been laid at the Riddler's feet.
Our leader, Doc Thompkins,
she thinks that she
knows what's good for you.
She thinks stapling a live
barracuda to someone's face
isn't damn good entertainment.
(CROWD BOOING)
Just get on with the show, Ed.
Okay, enough! What time is it?
ALL: Riddle time!
What time is it?
Lila!
(CROWD CHEERING)
Prepare the timer.
I can be broken
without being held.
Given, and then taken away.
Some people use me to deceive,
but when delivered, I
am the greatest gift of all.
What am I?
You stumped?
Of course I am.
You're the Riddler.
So, you give up?
LEE: No.
You're gonna give me the answer.
(LAUGHS)
Really? How's that?
Because deep down, you want to.
So, that's your plan. To
appeal to the inner Ed.
You played the wrong hand, Doc.
Ed is gone,
and I will not be manipulated
by you the way that dope was.
I didn't manipulate
him, I helped him.
No. No, you lied to him.
You promised to fix him.
And that pathetic
dust mite believed you,
causing me to be locked
inside of his feeble mind.
Okay, you have 10 seconds
left to find your answer!
So, prepare to lose.
But I know the answer now.
(SCOFFS)
You just gave it to me.
What are you talking about?
You're right. I told Ed I
would fix him, and I didn't.
I broke my promise.
And that, Riddler,
is the answer.
A promise.
(ALL CHEERING)
Well played.
We're only halfway through.
And I assure you,
you will not stump me.
Boo. (LAUGHING)
You need to take
us to your brother.
I can't do that.
What if he's nuttier
than the other one?
I'm nothing like Jerome!
Do you want me to put
you in a cell next to his?
Because that is
where this is heading.
And then what, Captain Gordon?
You couldn't hold him,
Arkham couldn't, I can.
And I will make sure
Jerome never escapes again.
- No, no, no. Jerome comes with us.
- (ALARM BEEPING)
And if you wanna make
this easier on yourself,
I suggest you stay
the hell out of the way.
Whoa, whoa, whoa!
The loonies are outside.
No, no.
How'd they find me?
Must've followed Jerome.
We need to move. Now.
(ALARM BLARING)
This is not good.
Is there another
way out of here?
Yes, but I'm not leaving Echo.
The loonies will
use her against us.
She's devoted her life to me.
We get you out first and
we can come back for her.
Deal?
As a child, I was
obsessed with labyrinths,
so I designed my house like one.
- You mean this place is a maze?
- Easy enough to get in.
I'm the only one who
knows the way out.
Stay close to me.
The maze is built on a hundred
acres. There are 73 dead ends.
I once invited the top maze designers
in the country to try to solve it.
One did. It took him three days.
GORDON: And how much further?
Not far. We just passed
the final switchback point.
If I knew this thing
was a hundred acres,
I would have stopped and
got a sandwich before we came.
Echo.
- Thank God you're okay.
- Hey, hey, hey. She's hypnotized.
(GROANS)
(ALL GRUNTING)
Echo. It's me.
It's me. Ow!
Gordon! Help!
Gordon!
She's a pistol.
Come on.
Echo, please. Where
are you taking me?
- I'm taking you to Jerome.
- No.
He'll do horrible
things to me. Echo!
Stop!
Let him go.
(ALL GRUNT)
(GROANS)
Thanks.
- He went that way.
- All right.
Jeremiah?
Let's try this way.
(SIGHS)
JEROME: Hello, brother.
(GASPS)
So, how you been?
Oh, you look great.
(LAUGHING)
To think I used to be
the handsome one, right?
How'd you find your
way through the maze?
Oh, bro, we might not
look the same anymore,
but we still think the same.
Plus, you used to draw those
stupid things all the time as a kid.
I paid attention.
Hey, Hat Head,
take Crane, find Jimbo and
his bearded sidekick. Kill them.
I've been waiting for
this moment for 15 years,
ever since you ran away in the
middle of the night like a coward.
- You're insane.
- Yeah.
And I tried telling Mom, but
she didn't want to listen to me.
You blame me for everything
that's gone wrong in your life,
but the truth is, Jerome,
you were born bad.
Born bad, huh?
So, that's why you made her
think that I tried to kill you, right?
- Yeah, we both...
- What was it again? What was it?
I put a blade to your
throat. No, no, no.
- I tried to light you on fire.
- We both know you wanted to.
Yeah, that was a
funny story, wasn't it?
Okay, maybe it didn't
happen exactly like that,
but I didn't have a
choice and I was right.
Huh?
You killed our mother.
She did deserve it though.
After that whore hid you
away, she gave up on me,
poisoned by your stories.
You turned everyone I
ever loved against me.
My own flesh and blood!
I guess it's like what they say,
"We all could go insane
with just one bad day."
I guess with you it's
more like one bad spray.
You'll see.
(LAUGHING)
- Listen to what I have to say.
- Oh, hell no!
You are not
hypnotizing me again!
(YELLING)
That's one way to do it.
Must go! Must go!
(EXCLAIMS)
What are you gonna
do to me, Jerome?
Come on. I'm gonna
kill you, of course.
But first...
I'm gonna drive you mad.
But don't worry,
you won't be alone.
All of Gotham will
be joining you, too.
Must go! Must go! They're
after me and the Scarecrow!
These guys just
don't give up, huh?
(HARVEY YELLING)
(GASPS)
Get any closer,
and I splatter him!
I'm gonna splatter broski.
No, you won't. If you wanted him
dead you would've killed him already.
(GIGGLES) He's
right. I'll see you soon.
- Mwah.
- (YELPS)
(JEROME LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
Okay, Doc.
You've had enough
time to think of a riddle.
I hope you've come
up with a good one.
I have.
Then ask away.
What three words
are said too much,
meant by few, but wanted by all?
(SCOFFS) That's your riddle?
You're kidding, right?
What's the answer?
Easy. I love...
(CLEARS THROAT)
(NYGMA SIGHS)
The answer is, I love...
I love what, Ed?
- That's not my name.
- Then what's the answer?
You tricked me.
You're trying to awaken
a love that isn't there.
If it isn't there,
then say the words.
I won't say it.
(CROWD BOOING)
MAN: Come on.
Say it.
Time's up.
(CROWD CHEERING)
Thank you.
What did I say?
(YELPING)
I can help you get Tabitha back!
I know how to
reverse your condition.
(GASPING)
Talk.
This barrel is from
Slaughter Swamp.
It turned you into what you are.
Talk.
Professor Hugo Strange is
the one man who can cure you.
Join me, and we will find him.
(COUGHING)
I thought I was going to
be stuck like this forever.
You don't have to be, friend.
Okay. I'll join you.
But you'd better deliver.
And I'm not your friend.
I can live with those terms.
(FOOTSTEPS APPROACHING)
Why did you open your
club in The Narrows?
You could've set up
shop anywhere in Gotham.
You wanted my attention.
I came back here because
the people love me.
People didn't come here
because they love you, Ed,
they came for the money.
But I can give them what
they want. I just need your help.
Why would I help you?
Because I know
what you really want.
You love me.
You've loved me all along.
You're wrong.
That was Ed.
Okay.
So, do it.
Kill me.
(GASPS)
What's your record for how many
banks you've robbed in one day?
Three. Why?
I think you can do better.
You're playing a
dangerous game, Lee.
I know.
(INDISTINCT CHATTER)
It's all right. Come on.
- Captain.
- It's okay.
This is Jeremiah Valeska,
Jerome's twin brother.
We need to put him
into protective custody.
Okay. Follow me.
Thank you.
Captain Gordon, I wouldn't
be alive if it weren't for you.
(SIGHS)
Hell of a day.
What are you thinking?
GORDON: Jerome told his brother
his plan was to turn Gotham mad.
How the hell is he
going to do that, Harvey?
I don't know. I
thought it already was.
(WHIRRING)
- (GUN CLICKS)
- (GRUNTS)
(WHIRRING)
(GUN CLICKS)
Damn.
(GUNSHOT)
(THUDS)
Doesn't even make
me feel better at all.
CRANE: Jerome.
The test subject has arrived.
Hmm.
A little large for a test
subject, don't you think?
He is not your test
subject. This is Grundy.
He will make a welcome
addition to the team.
Mmm-hmm. Mmm-hmm.
I like him. He's scary.
Good thinking, Mr. Oswald.
Nice to meet you, big fellow.
Ow!
Ah!
- Test subject?
- Here to test your plan,
an unwilling businessman.
MAN: No, no, no! Please, please.
Please don't hurt me.
CRANE: Oh, this
won't hurt a bit.
(MAN GROANS)
(MAN COUGHING)
(MAN LAUGHING MANIACALLY)
(BOTH LAUGHING)
Oh, we're gonna
need a lot more of this!
(BOTH CONTINUE LAUGHING)
(SCREAMING)
English-US-SDH